Guide to the William Watson Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Maureen Pring Watson Gift, 1867-1948; Series II; 3.34; (8 boxes)
  - WRITINGS BY WILLIAM WATSON
    - Poems
      - "The Threatened Towers" (2 copies), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 184)
      - "The Three Kinds of Song" and "Youth and the Muse" (Box 5, Folder 185)
      - "The Thundershower" (Box 5, Folder 186)
      - "The Thwarted Flower" (2 copies), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 187)
      - "Thy Heart Is Mine", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 188)
        See also: Music, Box 6, folder 228, and Music, Oversize, Box 12, folder 379
      - "Thy Passionate Breast", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 189)
      - "Till Ireland Has Her Own" (2 copies)
      - "To A. E. H.", 1917 Mar 21 (Box 5, Folder 190)
      - "To a Bereaved One" and "One of the Fallacies" (2 copies) (Box 5, Folder 191)
        See also: "On a Certain Statue of Liberty" and "To One Bereaved," Oversize, Box 14, folder 389
      - "To a Government", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 192)
      - "To an Oracular Publicist," typescript, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 193)
      - "To Certain Nebulae", n.d.
      - "To James Churton Collins", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 194)
      - "To Lord Fisher", n.d.
      - "To Milton, on His Lycidas", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 195)
      - "To One Bereaved", n.d.
      - "To One in His Grave", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 196)
      - "To Roosevelt", n.d.
      - "Too Soon" (2 copies), n.d.
      - "A Triad of Poets", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 197)
      - "Tu Quoque", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 198)
      - "Two Songs", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 199)
      - "An Ultra-Democrat", 1914 (Box 5, Folder 200)
      - "The Unreconciled" (2 copies), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 201)
      - "Verses to Henry C. Montgomery, Esq., of Belfast, Written Near Windermere, at Christmas, 1917", 1917 Dec (Box 5, Folder 202)
      - "A Vignette", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 203)
      - "The Visitor Abhorred", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 204)
      - "The Wasted Lures", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 205)
      - "Wheresoever", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 206)
      - "Whither Afar?", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 207)
      - "The Wizard's Crux" (2 copies), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 208)
      - "The Yellow Pansy", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 209)
      - "The Yesterdays and the Morrows" (4 copies and 3 fragments), 1934-35, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 210)
      - "Youth and the Muse," with notes appended (Box 5, Folder 211)
        See also: "The Three Kinds of Song," Box 5, folder 185
      - Unidentified poems and fragments, 1914-29, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 212)
    - Other Writings
      - Inscriptions cut from books and other signatures, 1892-1925, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 213-218)
      - "Ireland Arisen," essay, 2 drafts
      - "The King Without Peer," play, 1910 Apr 14 (Box 6, Folder 219)
        Also titled: "King Alfred" Date from publisher's stamp
      - "A List of Books by Sir William Watson in Chronological Order," holograph, n.d.
      - "Notes for a Lecture on the Appreciation of Poetry," typed transcript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 220)
      - "Pencraft: A Plea for the Older Ways," essay, [ca. 1917] (Box 6, Folder 221)
      - "The Poet's Place in the Scheme of Life," essay, [ca. 1912-13] (Box 6, Folder 222)
      - Unidentified fragments and notes, 1935, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 223)
  - MUSIC BY WILLIAM WATSON
    - "Elfin Wardance," for piano, copyist's manuscript, with corrections, n.d.
    - "Fickle Spring: Morceau for the Pianoforte," fragment, copyist's manuscript, n.d.
    - "I Care Not," song for voice and piano, holograph with corrections (Box 6, Folder 224)
    - "Lady Coy's Refusal," song for voice and piano, copyist's manuscript, with corrections
    - "The Lighthouse of Love," song for voice and piano, copyist's manuscript (2 copies)
    - "The Lute Player," song for voice and piano, words by WW, music by Frances Allitsen, reproduced from manuscript
    - "The Lute Player," (London: Edwin Ashdown, c1895, E. A. 32691), with manuscript annotations (Box 6, Folder 225)
    - "March of the Peacemakers," for piano, copyist's manuscript (2 copies), n.d.
      Also titled: "March of the Friends of Freedom"
    - "O Placid Moon," song for voice and piano, copyist's manuscript (2 copies, one with corrections)
    - "Our Land," hymn, printed sheet, signed (Box 6, Folder 226)
    - "St. George's, Windsor," hymn, words by WW, music by George Job Elvey, printed excerpt from a hymnal (Box 6, Folder 227)
    - "Thy Heart Is Mine," song for voice and piano, holograph, with corrections (Box 6, Folder 228)
    - "Thy Heart Is Mine," copyist's manuscript, with corrections, n.d.
  - WILLIAM WATSON PERSONAL PAPERS
    - Locks of hair
      - MPW (Box 7, Folder 229)
      - WW (Box 7, Folder 230)
      - WW, with holograph notes by MPW, 1919 Feb 24 (Box 7, Folder 231)
      - WW (Box 7, Folder 232)
    - Papers concerning Robinson Watson
      - Legal documents, 1899-1920 (Box 7, Folder 233)
      - WW letters to RW, typed transcripts, 1893-94, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 234)
      - John Lane letters to RW, typed transcripts, 1909-10, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 235)
      - John Lane letters to other recipients, 1908-10 (Box 7, Folder 236)
      - James Shield letters to WW, 1900-10 (Box 7, Folder 237)
      - RW letters to WW, 1909, 1918 (Box 7, Folder 238)
      - RW letters to John Lane and James Shield, 1908-10 (Box 7, Folder 239)
      - RW letters to other recipients, 1898-1917, n.d., typed transcripts (Box 7, Folder 240)
      - William R. Watson letters (nephew of WW?), 1908 Oct (Box 7, Folder 241)
      - Other letters (Box 7, Folder 242)
    - Other Papers
      - The Book of Common Prayer (London: William Collins, Sons, & Co.) (Box 7, Folder 243)
        Preliminary pages are annotated in holograph regarding WW's marriage and the birth of his daughters
      - Document granting permission to Edith Harrhy to set WW's poems to music, typescript, signed, 1934 Oct 19 (Box 7, Folder 244)
      - "Father Lights a Fire, by Rhona," manuscript, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 245)
      - Marriage certificate, 1909 Aug 10 (Box 7, Folder 246)
        With a statement regarding the marriage written by Mary Pring and signed by MP and MPW
      - Mechanical pencil, engraved "William Watson", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 247)
      - "Police Certificate of Identity," with photograph attached, 1918 May 29 (Box 7, Folder 248)
      - Recipe for a pharmacist, holograph, signed, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 249)
      - Visiting cards, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 250)
  - MAUREEN PRING WATSON PAPERS
    - Correspondence
      - National Library of Ireland, Genealogical Office, to Sean O'Sullivan, about MPW, 1946 Dec 19 (Box 8, Folder 251)
      - Pring, Harry (father of MPW), 1905 Oct 9 (Box 8, Folder 252)
      - Ratcliffe, Dorothy Una, 1948 Jun 7 (Box 8, Folder 253)
      - [Sutter?], G. K., 1935 Jun, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 254)
      - Swayze, Walter E., 1947-48 (Box 8, Folder 255)
    - Writings
      - "England, Are You Proud?," biography of WW, typescript (2 copies) and portfolio (Box 8, Folder 256-259)
      - Letter to her daughters concerning Seumas MacManus, typescript, photocopy, 1946 Aug 20 (Box 8, Folder 260)
      - Notes concerning Coulson Kernahan, holograph, 1937 (Box 8, Folder 261)
    - Other Papers
      - Application for United States copyright for musical composition "I Care Not," printed form completed in holograph, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 262)
      - Copies and drafts of letters, in the hand of WW, 1925, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 263)
      - List of chapters for a biography of WW, possibly by Walter E. Swayze, typescript, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 264)
      - Photograph of Pic & Coffee Shop, Asheville, NC, and business license, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 265)
      - Statement for purchase of water in Ashville, NC, signed by MPW, 1948 Oct (Box 8, Folder 266)
      - United States immigrant identification card, with photograph attached, 1939 Apr 19 (Box 8, Folder 267)
      - Visiting card, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 268)
  - PRINTED MATERIAL
    - Clippings, 1895-1946, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 269)
    - "Marriage of a Famous Poet," broadside, Daily Mail, [1909?]
    - "Poem to America, by William Watson" broadside (photograph), Evening News, 1917 Feb 12 (Box 9, Folder 270)
    - Transcriptions from printed biographical sources, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 271)
    - Ephemera, 1921, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 272)
  - DRAWINGS
    - Andrews, Edward William, 2 portraits of WW, charcoal, 1892-93
    - Crofts, Henrietta, "Wordsworth's Grave," pen and ink, inscribed on verso of frame by Arthur C. Benson to WW (Box 9, Folder 273)
    - Watson, Geraldine, "Mother By Me," drawing of MPW, pen and ink (Box 9, Folder 274)
    - Unidentified, "M. W. in Bed," drawing of MPW, pencil and watercolor, 1944 Feb (Box 9, Folder 275)
    - Unidentified, "William Watson's Left Hand," pencil, 1926 May 30 (Box 9, Folder 276)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS
    - People
      - Watson, William, [1867-1935] (Box 9, Folder 277-282)
        See also: photograph attached to "Police Certificate of Identity," Box 7, folder 248
      - Watson, Maureen Pring, [1888-ca. 1920?] (Box 9, Folder 283-284)
        Includes photographs of MPW with her daughters Rhona and Geraldine Watson and her mother Mary Pring
        See also: photograph attached to "United States Immigrant Identification Card," Box 8, folder 267
      - Cox, Marion, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 285)
      - Lane, John (photograph of a painting), n.d. (Box 9, Folder 286)
      - Pring, Harry (father of MPW), n.d. (Box 9, Folder 287)
      - [Pring, Harry, and John Stanley Pring?] (brothers of MPW) (Box 9, Folder 288)
      - Pring, Mary, as a child (mother of MPW), tintype, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 289)
      - Robinson, Margaret, in old age (maternal grandmother of WW) (Box 9, Folder 290)
      - Watson, Geraldine (daughter of WW and MPW) (Box 9, Folder 291)
      - Watson, Rhona, at about 18 years old (daughter of WW and MPW) (Box 9, Folder 292)
      - Watson, Robinson (brother of WW), n.d. (Box 9, Folder 293)
      - ----- (grandmother of MPW) (Box 9, Folder 294)
      - Unidentified, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 295)
    - Places
      - Dundalgan Castle, Dundalk, Ireland (home of MPW) (Box 9, Folder 296)
      - Grave of Harry Pring (father of MPW), n.d. (Box 9, Folder 297)
      - Grave of John Keats, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 298)
      - Grave of John and Dorothy Watson (parents of WW) and WW (Box 9, Folder 299)
      - North End House, gate, Rottingdean (Box 9, Folder 300)
      - Unidentified, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 301)
- George S. MacManus Purchase, 1879-1952; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  Purchased from George S. MacManus on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1980.
  - WILLIAM WATSON CORRESPONDENCE
    - Letters From WW
      - Austin, Alfred, 1887-91 (Box 10, Folder 302)
      - Bromley, James, 1891-1906 (Box 10, Folder 303-305)
        Includes a bank check signed by WW; accompanied by notes written by R. W. D. Holland
      - Cox, M. R., 1891 Aug 27 (Box 10, Folder 306)
      - Farrar, Frederick William, [ca. 1898?] (Box 10, Folder 307)
      - Fletcher, J. S. (Joseph Smith), 1926 Feb 4 (Box 10, Folder 308)
      - Ford, J. D., [1882-ca. 1890] (Box 10, Folder 309)
      - Hart, Lionel, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 310)
      - Huxley, Leonard (draft), 1923 Jun 5
      - Noble, Essie, [ca. 1880?] (Box 10, Folder 311)
      - Noble, Irene, 1893 Nov (Box 10, Folder 312)
      - Noble, James Ashcroft, [1879-87?] (Box 10, Folder 313)
      - Richards, Grant, 1921 Oct 8 (Box 10, Folder 314)
      - Schirmacher, Dora, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 315)
        Accompanied by 10 poems by WW, holograph
      - Simon, Miss, [1887?] Sep 29 (Box 10, Folder 316)
      - Twentieth Century (journal?), n.y. Dec 10 (Box 10, Folder 317)
      - Watts-Dunton, Theodore, 1913 May 24 (Box 10, Folder 318)
    - Letters To WW
      - Asquith, H. H. (Herbert Henry), 1905 Jan 8 (Box 10, Folder 319)
        Accompanied by an envelope dated 1909
        See also: photograph of first page, annotated by WW, Box 2, folder 50
      - Benson, Arthur Christopher, 1913 Apr 9 (Box 10, Folder 320)
      - Collins, John Churton, 1895 Jan 3 (Box 10, Folder 321)
      - Huxley, Leonard, 1923 Jun 4 (Box 10, Folder 322)
      - Milford, Humphrey Sumner, Sir (copy), 1912 Apr 22 (Box 10, Folder 323)
      - Smith, Reginald John, 1912-16 (Box 10, Folder 324)
      - Spender, John A., 1912 Mar 27 (Box 10, Folder 325)
      - Thornton Butterworth (publisher), 1929 Feb-Jun (Box 10, Folder 326)
        Typescript copy of a letter signed by Tresham Lever Accompanied by a statement by WW, typescript
      - Watts, George Frederick, 1895 Sep 1 (Box 10, Folder 327)
  - OTHER CORRESPONDENCE CONCERNING WILLIAM WATSON
    - Armstrong, Harry Gloster, Sir. TLS to Maureen Pring Watson, 1931 Jan 21 (Box 10, Folder 328)
    - Johnson, Robert Underwood. Letters to F. C. Owlett, 1930-31 (Box 10, Folder 329)
      Accompanied by holograph notes by Owlett regarding a testimonial fund for WW
    - Johnson, Robert Underwood. Letters to Maureen Pring Watson, 1930-31 (Box 10, Folder 330)
    - Young, Jessie Brett. Letter to Maureen Pring Watson, 1933 Feb 15 (Box 10, Folder 331)
  - WRITINGS BY WILLIAM WATSON
    - "Callow love", n.d. (Box 10, Folder 332)
    - "Earthworship", 1924 Aug (Box 10, Folder 333)
    - "Ireland Arisen," title page proof, 1921 (Box 10, Folder 334)
    - "Ode on the Day of the Coronation of King Edward VII," excerpt, n.d.
    - "To J. D. Ford, After Receiving a Charming Present", 1882 Jan 30 (Box 10, Folder 335)
    - "To James Bromley, of Lathom, Lancashire", 18[89?] May 20 (Box 10, Folder 336)
  - R. W. D. HOLLAND PAPERS CONCERNING WILLIAM WATSON
    - ALS from Leonard Knowles, with letters from Maureen Pring Watson to Knowles, 1936, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 337)
    - Letters from H. J. Penny, 1952 Mar-Jun (Box 10, Folder 338)
    - Notes concerning WW correspondence (Box 10, Folder 339)
- Materials From Other Sources, 1889-1940; Series IV; 0.42; (1 box)
  Acquired by gift and purchase from various sources, as indicated on individual folders.
  - WILLIAM WATSON CORRESPONDENCE
    - Adcock, Arthur St. John, 1912-26 (Box 11, Folder 340)
    - Bell, Mackenzie, 1892 Feb-Sep (Box 11, Folder 341)
      With 3 ALS, copies from Bell to WW
    - Blunt, Wilfrid Scawen, 1889, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 342)
    - Clodd, Edward, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 343)
      Acc #: 19700601-a
    - [Courtney, Janet Elizabeth Hogarth?], n.y. Jul 21 (Box 11, Folder 344)
      To "Dear Lady Courtney"
    - Dixon, Miss Hepworth, 1925 Nov 4 (Box 11, Folder 345)
    - Ely, -----, 1912 Mar 29 (Box 11, Folder 346)
      Acc #: 19820518-b
    - Frith, J. Cartwright, 1914-30 (Box 11, Folder 347-348)
      Includes letters from MPW to Frith and a letter, draft, from Frith to MPW
      Acc #: 19920817-i
    - Griffith, William, 1912 Apr-May (Box 11, Folder 349)
      Acc #: 19630327-b
    - Hind, Lewis, n.y. Jan 27 (Box 11, Folder 349a)
      Acc #: 20000317-t
    - Lane, John, 1903 May 28 (Box 11, Folder 350)
    - Lane, John (copy), 1914 Sep 25 (Box 11, Folder 351)
    - R. & R. Clark (publisher), n.d. (Box 11, Folder 352)
      Acc #: 19581229-a
    - Shorter, Clement King, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 353)
      Acc #: 19840111-a
    - Whelen, ----, [1898?] (Box 11, Folder 354)
      Acc #: 19680806-a
    - Winchester, Clarence (with "The Lighthouse of Love," poem, enclosed), 1929 Apr 15 (Box 11, Folder 355)
      Acc #: 19701210-a
    - Zaehnsdorf, [Joseph William?], 1901 Jan 24 (Box 11, Folder 356)
      Acc #: 20000124-e
    - Unidentified, n.y. Nov 12 (Box 11, Folder 357)
      Acc #: 19660804-a
  - POEMS BY WILLIAM WATSON
    - "Apologia", n.d. (Box 11, Folder 357a)
      Title from annotation in unidentified hand on verso
      Acc #: 20000602-j
    - "Beautiful Snow" inscribed to Harris B. Dick, with typed transcript, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 358)
      Acc #: 19830511-a
    - "The Elf-King's Daughter", n.d.
      Acc #: 19591223-a
    - "The Enamoured Lute", n.d.
    - "Hellas, Hail!", 1897
    - "The Lighthouse of Love"
      See: enclosure with letter from Clarence Winchester to WW, Box 11, folder 355
    - "A Night-ride", 1878 Nov 25 (Box 11, Folder 358a)
      Autograph manuscript, signed
      Acc #: 20010206-c
    - "Poems by William Watson, Published and Unpublished: The Original Manuscripts," in bound volume (Box 11, Folder 359)
      Acc #: 19950502-a
    - "Prelude", n.d. (Box 11, Folder 360)
      Acc #: 19820518-a
    - "Sonnet: Our Eastern Treasure (from Ver Tenebrosum, 1885)", n.d. (Box 11, Folder 361)
      Acc #: 19810903-a
    - "They and We" (Box 11, Folder 362)
    - "The Tomb of Burns," clipping from The Spectator, 1895 Jul 6 (Box 11, Folder 363)
    - "Wordsworth's Grave and Other Poems," bound volume, [ca.1890] (Box 11, Folder 364)
      Acc #: 19680426-a
  - OTHER WILLIAM WATSON PAPERS
    - Clippings, 1940, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 365)
    - Drawing of an unidentified man, pencil, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 366)
    - "The Old Dairy House, South Chard," photograph postcard, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 367)
    - Photograph portrait of WW, signed, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 368)
- Oversize, 4.59; (3 boxes)
  - "I Care Not," song (in Series I), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 369)
  - "Thy Heart is Mine," song (in Series I), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 370)
  - Letters from WW to Leonard Huxley (drafts) (in Series II), 1923 May-Jun (Box 12, Folder 371)
  - "Elfin Wardance," for piano (in Series II), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 372)
  - "Fickle Spring: Morceau for the Pianoforte," fragment (in Series II), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 373)
  - "Lady Coy's Refusal," song (in Series II), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 374)
  - "The Lighthouse of Love," song (2 copies) (in Series II), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 375)
  - "The Lute Player," song (in Series II), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 376)
  - "March of the Peacemakers," for piano (2 copies) (in Series II), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 377)
  - "O Placid Moon," song (2 copies) (in Series II), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 378)
  - "Thy Heart Is Mine," song (in Series II), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 379)
  - "England, Are You Proud?", p. 55 from first of two copies (In Series II) (Box 12, Folder 379a)
  - Letter from WW to Leonard Huxley (draft) (in Series III), 1923 Jun 5 (Box 12, Folder 380)
  - Poems (in Series I), 1880-1915, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 381)
  - Andrews, Edward William, 2 portraits of WW (in Series II), 1892-93 (Box 13, Folder 382-383)
  - "Ode on the Day of the Coronation of King Edward VII," excerpt (in Series III), n.d. (Box 13, Folder 384)
  - Poems (in Series IV), 1897, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 385)
  - Poems, "A-D" (in Series II), 1921-23, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 386)
  - Poems, "E-F" (in Series II), 1904-18, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 387)
  - Poems, "I-M" (in Series II), 1881-1921, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 388)
  - Poems, "N-R" (in Series II), 1919, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 389)
  - Poems, "S" (in Series II), 1919, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 390)
  - Poems, "T" (in Series II), 1915, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 391)
  - Poems, "Y" and Unidentified (in Series II) (Box 14, Folder 392)
  - "Ireland Arisen," essay, 2 drafts (in Series II) (Box 14, Folder 393-394)
  - "A List of Books by Sir William Watson in Chronological Order (in Series II), n.d. (Box 14, Folder 395)
  - Oversize clippings (in Series II), 1912-30, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 396)
  - "Wordsworth's Grave," galley proof (in Series I), 1887 (Box Bsd, folder 397)
  - "Marriage of a Famous Poet," broadside, Daily Mail (in Series II), [1909?] (Box Bsd, folder 398)
- Restricted Fragile, (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted Fragile. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 9, folder 269 (Box 15, Folder 399)
  - Box 7, folder 247 (Box 15, Folder 400)